J. Westbrook Pegler Papers
J. Westbrook Pegler Papers
1940-1962
Pegler, J. Westbrook (James Westbrook), 1894-1969.
5.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American journalist, columnist, distributed by King Features Syndicate. Collection includes newspaper columns (1942-1962) in the form of typed final copies, clippings of published columns, and a few letters to the editor of the Syracuse Post Standard.
149467
Biographical History
James Westbrook Pegler (1894-1969) was an American journalist. Born in Minneapolis, Minnesota on August 2, 1894, he was educated at the Lane Technical School and at Loyola University in Chicago. He received an honorary LL.D. from Knox College in 1943. He was a correspondent on the European staff of United Press during World War I (1916-1918) and then served in the U.S. Navy (1918-1919); later he was sports editor of the United News, the Chicago Tribune, the New York World-Telegram, and the Chicago Daily News. In 1944 he moved his syndicated column to King Features Syndicate. His collected columns were published in several books: 'Taint Right (1936), Dissenting Opinions of Mister Westbrook Pegler (1938), and George Spelvin, American (1942).
In his syndicated columns, Pegler criticized many American figures and institutions, including the Supreme Court, the tax system, labor unions, and every President from Herbert Hoover to John F. Kennedy. In 1962 he lost his contract with King Features Syndicate due to outspoken criticisms of executives of its parent company, the Hearst Corporation.
Pegler was a member of the National Press Club and received numerous awards for his work. In 1941 he received the Pulitzer Prize for reporting for his expose of racketeering in Hollywood labor unions. In 1942 he was named one of the country's best adult columnists and in 1944 he won the Gold Medal from the Nassau Bar Association. Other awards include the National Headlines Club Award (twice), the American Legion Award, and the Distinguished Service Medal of Army and Navy Union.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The J. Westbrook Pegler Papers consists of printed materials and writings.
The Printed material consists of clippings and letters to the editor of the Syracuse Post Standard. One set of clippings includes an exchange of opinions in the form of published columns between Grace Lewis - another Post Standard columnist - and Pegler.
The Writings consist of Pegler's numerous columns written between 1942 and 1962, including both Pegler's typed final copies and clippings of published columns from the Syracuse Post Standard. The original envelopes in which the column clippings were received are included with the respective clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Pegler, J. Westbrook (James Westbrook), 1894-1969.; Journalism.; Journalists -- United States.; Newspapers -- Sections, columns, etc.; Clippings (information artifacts); Newspaper columns.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Printed material
  - Clippings, Pegler/Lewis, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1950-1951; undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to the editor, 1950-1951; undated; filed together by Pegler (Box 1)
  - Letters to the editor, 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - The Saturday Evening Post, 14 Sep 1940 (Oversize 1)
- Writings
  - Columns, 1942 Nov-Dec; clippings (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1943 Jan-Mar, May, Jul, Nov; clippings (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1944 Feb, Sep-Nov; clippings (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1945 Jan-Feb, Apr-May, Aug-Sep; 1945, undated; clippings; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1946 Feb, May-Dec; 1946, undated; clippings; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1947 Jan-Dec; clippings; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1948 Jan-Dec; clippings; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1949 Jan-Dec; clippings; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1950 Jan-Dec; clippings; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1951 Jan-Apr; typed final copy; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Columns, 1951 Jul-Dec; typed final copy; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Columns, 1951 Jan-Dec; clippings; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Columns, 1952 Jan-Feb; typed final copy; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Columns, 1952 Mar, May-Dec; typed final copy; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Columns, 1952 Jan-Mar, May-June; clippings (Box 3)
  - Columns, 1952 Jul-Dec; 1952, undated; clippings; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Columns, 1953 Jan-Oct; typed final copy; 10 folders (Box 4)
  - Columns, 1953 Nov-Dec; typed final copy; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Columns, 1953 Jan-Dec; clippings; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Columns, 1954 Jan-Feb; typed final copy; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Columns, 1954 Mar-Dec; typed final copy; 10 folders (Box 11)
  - Columns, 1954 Jan-Feb; clippings (Box 11)
  - Columns, 1955 Jan; typed final copy (Box 11)
  - Columns, 1955 Feb-Dec; 1956 Jan-Mar; typed final copy; 14 folders (Box 5)
  - Columns, 1956 Apr-Dec; 1957 Jan-Apr; typed final copy; 13 folders (Box 6)
  - Columns, 1957 May-Dec; 1958 Jan-Jul, Sep-Dec;; 1959 Jan-Feb; typed final copy; 14 folders (Box 7)
  - Columns, 1959 Mar-Aug, Oct-Dec; 1960 Jan-Oct; typed final copy; 10 folders (Box 8)
  - Columns, 1960 Nov-Dec; 1961 Jan-Dec;; 1962 Jan-Aug; typed final copy; 11 folders (Box 9)